<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>https://github.com/tamouse/swaac</id>
  <title>Tamouse&#39;s Software as a Craft blog</title>
  <updated>2020-12-09T22:47:55-06:00</updated>
    <entry>
      <id>https://github.com/tamouse/swaac/blob/master/posts/2020/12/2020-12-09-til-deleting-nested-objects-in-accepts-nested-attributes-for.md</id>
      <updated>2020-12-09T22:47:55-06:00</updated>
      <title>2020-12-09-til-deleting-nested-objects-in-accepts-nested-attributes-for</title>
      <content>---
title: &quot;TIL: Deleting nested objects in accepts_nested_attributes_for&quot;
Area: SWaaC
Created: 2020-05-04T12:46:00
Link: https://api.rubyonrails.org/v5.1.7/classes/ActiveRecord/NestedAttributes/ClassMethods.html#method-i-accepts_nested_attributes_for
Published: 2020-12-09T22:46
tags: Rails, attributes, nesting
topic: Ruby and Rails
---

&gt; By default the associated records are protected from being destroyed. If you want to destroy any of the associated records through the attributes hash, you have to enable it first using the `:allow_destroy` option. This will allow you to also use the `_destroy` key to destroy existing records:

```ruby
class Member &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
  has_many :posts
  accepts_nested_attributes_for :posts, allow_destroy: true
end

params = { member: {
  posts_attributes: [{ id: &#39;2&#39;, _destroy: &#39;1&#39; }]
}}

member.attributes = params[:member]
member.posts.detect { |p| p.id == 2 }.marked_for_destruction? # =&gt; true
member.posts.length # =&gt; 2
member.save
member.reload.posts.length # =&gt; 1
```

Up earlier in the page, the `_destroy` is mentioned:

&gt; For each hash that does not have an id key a new record will be instantiated, unless the hash also contains a `_destroy` key that evaluates to true.

So apparently it doesn&#39;t matter what the actual value of the key is, as long as it&#39;s *truthy*

In the controller, make sure to permit the `_destroy` attribute as well.

## an example

If this is the row in your form that contains a subitem to go along with the update of the item:

```html
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot; id=&quot;item_subitem_2_row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;hidden&quot; name=&quot;item[subitem][2][id]&quot; value=&quot;12&quot; id=&quot;item_subitem_2_id&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;!-- rest of row fields --&gt;
  &lt;button type=&quot;button&quot; id=&quot;item_subitem_2_delete_button&quot;&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;trash-can-icon&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
```

you would need to extract that row and replace it with:

```html
&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;hidden&quot; name=&quot;item[subitem][2][id]&quot; value=&quot;12&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;input type=&quot;hidden&quot; name=&quot;item[subitem][2][_destroy]&quot; value=&quot;1&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
```

The `id` on the `input` field in the first code snippet is typically auto-generated by Rails form helpers. The &quot;destroy&quot; hidden input doesn&#39;t really need an `id` field as it won&#39;t be referred to by the DOM. Unless you need to for some reason, then add one.

Then some JavaScript is necessary to detect the delete subitem button click, and perform the replacement.

Theoretically, which means I haven&#39;t been able to try this yet, the `_destroy` field could be already defined for the form row, and you set the value of it to something truthy on button click, and hide the row.

-----

Source: &lt;https://api.rubyonrails.org/v5.1.7/classes/ActiveRecord/NestedAttributes/ClassMethods.html#method-i-accepts_nested_attributes_for&gt;
</content>
      <author>
        <name>Tamara Temple</name>
        <email>tamara@tamouse.org</email>
      </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <id>https://github.com/tamouse/swaac/blob/master/posts/2020/03/2020-03-23-honouring-colour-scheme-in-css.md</id>
      <updated>2020-10-21T11:31:51-05:00</updated>
      <title>2020-03-23-honouring-colour-scheme-in-css</title>
      <content>---
title: &quot;Honouring the user&#39;s preferred colour scheme in CSS&quot;
date: 2020-03-23T03:32
category: css
tags: [colour-scheme, dark-mode, light-mode, react, styled-components]
---

How do I honour the user&#39;s chosen preferred colour scheme in the CSS I&#39;m writing? Recently MacOS introduced dark mode in Mojave, and further added a shifting light and dark mode to match the time of day in Catalina. I&#39;d like my sites, but more importantly, my React apps to follow this.


## Background ##

The W3C has defined a media query, `prefers-color-scheme` ([Defined in Media Queries Level 5 Draft, March 2020](https://drafts.csswg.org/mediaqueries-5/#descdef-media-prefers-color-scheme &quot;Still a draft&quot;)). It has [some implementations](https://caniuse.com/#search=prefers-color-scheme) already. At least it&#39;s on the majors, so it&#39;s probably okay to use.

## Media query ##

The check to see what colour scheme the user has set is done with a media query:

``` css
@media screen and (prefers-color-scheme: light) {
  /* settings for light scheme */
}
@media screen and (prefers-color-scheme: dark) {
  /* settings for dark scheme */
}
```

So this is clearly possible in regular CSS.

## Using in styled-components ##

Since I most often code in React, and most often use `styled-components` library to implement CSS-in-JS, I need a way that this will work. Turns out it&#39;s not so bad, using SC&#39;s `ThemeProvider`.

In your theme file, set up the various colours, with a group for light mode and another group for dark mode:

``` rjsx
const colors = {
    light: {
        primaryText: &quot;#333&quot;,
        primaryBg: &quot;#FFF&quot;,
        // and so on
    },
    dark: {
        primaryText: &quot;#F2F2F2&quot;,
        primaryBg: &quot;#000&quot;,
        // and so on
    },
    common: {
        // colors that work for both
    }
};

export default {
    colors
};

```

Where I wrap react components with the SC ThemeProvider, I can import and provide the theme as usual:

``` rjsx
import React from &quot;react&quot;;
import { ThemeProvider} from &#39;styled-components&#39;;
import theme from &quot;../../theme&quot;;

function App({ children }) {
    return (
        &lt;ThemeProvider theme={theme} &gt;
          {children}
        &lt;/ThemeProvider&gt;
    );
}

export default App;
```

Then later, in the styled compeonent, this happens:

``` rjsx

import styled from &#39;styled-components&#39;;

export const SomeSection = styled.section`
  color: ${props =&gt; props.theme.colors.light.primaryText};
  backgound-color: ${props =&gt; props.theme.colors.light.primaryBg};

  @media screen and (prefers-color-scheme: light) {
    color: ${props =&gt; props.theme.colors.light.primaryText};
    backgound-color: ${props =&gt; props.theme.colors.light.primaryBg};
  }
  @media screen and (prefers-color-scheme: dark) {
    color: ${props =&gt; props.theme.colors.dark.primaryText};
    backgound-color: ${props =&gt; props.theme.colors.dark.primaryBg};
  }
`
```
</content>
      <author>
        <name>Tamara Temple</name>
        <email>tamara@tamouse.org</email>
      </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <id>https://github.com/tamouse/swaac/blob/master/posts/2020/10/TIL-scoped-uniqueness-validation-syntax.md</id>
      <updated>2020-10-21T11:30:09-05:00</updated>
      <title>TIL-scoped-uniqueness-validation-syntax</title>
      <content>## Keywords:

- Ruby
- Rails
- Validators
- ActiveRecord
- Uniqueness

## Introduction

In Rails versions prior to 5.1, the standard accepted way to do a scoped uniqueness validation was by using the `validate_uniqueness_of` method:

``` ruby
class Subcategory &lt; ApplicationRecord

  belongs_to :category
  
  validate_presence of :slug
  validate_uniqueness_of :slug, scope: :category_id
end
```

With Rails 5.2, the longer forms are being deprecated, in favour of using the `validates` method instead.

In the api docs, however, the uniqueness validator isn&#39;t discussed, not even an example.

Luckily, I had rubocop set up to complain about the use of the older methods, and told it to fix the failures it found.

The new syntax would be:

``` ruby
class Subcategory &lt; ApplicationRecord

  belongs_to :category
  
  validates :slug, presence: true
  validates :slug, uniqueness: { scope: :category_id }
end
```

</content>
      <author>
        <name>Tamara Temple</name>
        <email>tamara@tamouse.org</email>
      </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <id>https://github.com/tamouse/swaac/blob/master/posts/Tech/gdi-classes.org</id>
      <updated>2020-05-23T16:52:21-05:00</updated>
      <title>GDI</title>
      <content>* GDI
** Slack convos
*** Discussion in #random about job salaries
    CAPTURE_DATE: [2017-06-05 Mon 15:45]

    #+BEGIN_QUOTE

 OP [1 hour ago]
 Hey all, I have a question that I have been struggling with for a bit. I am currently working through a bootcamp for full stack development and would like to start getting organized for the job search. I am starting to watch job postings and some ask what my preferred salary would be. I spent many years as a national park ranger, which means low pay and no chance at negotiating starting pay either. I have tried to look around at what the starting pay would be for staying in the twin cities but find reports on average salaries of experienced developers. Does anyone have resources on this or advice on what to ask for and how much to negotiate? I just don&#39;t know what to even ask for as a salary aside from making sure it pays the bills. Feel free to DM too if you would prefer. THANKS!

 R1 [1 hour ago]
 @OP: 1st things 1st, never mention your previous salary. Especially since it doesn’t apply to your next role as a dev.

 R1 [1 hour ago]
 2nd things 2nd, take a look at glassdoor, linkedin, and indeed. heck even the gov websites with salary averages to start getting a range.

 R1 [1 hour ago]
 then think about your life, lifestyle, I came up with a minimum I am comfortable with and then I keep that to myself.

 R1 [1 hour ago]
 I ask for 10-20k higher, depending on the company

 R1 [1 hour ago]
 My one phrase of advice when it comes to this is “The worst thing they can say is no, and even if they say no, it’s probably a maybe” (edited)

 R1 [1 hour ago]
 Know what you’re bringing to the table, some people will try to use your bootcamp only experience as a negative against you, it’s not. It’s a positive. It speaks to your thirst to learn, ability to learn and adapt quickly, passion and so much more.

 R1 [1 hour ago]
 People often underestimate what it means to basically change your whole life overnight when it comes to deciding to go to a bootcamp

 R1 [1 hour ago]
 anyways rant over… That’s my advice!

 R1 [1 hour ago]
 I bet @R5 has great advice on this as well

 OP [1 hour ago]
 thanks! that helps get me started

 R1 [1 hour ago]
 anytime. Congrats on getting ready to get out there!!

 R2 [1 hour ago]
 Yes yes yes. I second everything @R1 just mentioned. @R5 brought up the “never mention your previous salary” comment the other day. This is so key. Keep in mind that when a company posts a job, they already have a budget in mind. Let them share that first!

 R2 [1 hour ago]
 Not everyone will do that, and some might be cranky if you stay firm (this just happened to me) but it’s definitely worth a try.

 R2 [1 hour ago]
 We had a negotiating GDI workshop about a year ago that I found so valuable. Go in to the discussion with three numbers in your mind: the number that would just blow your socks off and make you crazy happy, a number that seems fair, reasonable and makes you excited, and a minimum number that you are willing to walk away from if they don’t meet. Keep these to yourself, but start with your high in the sky number and go from there :slightly_smiling_face:

 R3 [1 hour ago]
 Sometimes a company will ask you also what you used to make. When they ask me what I was making at my last job, I always lie and tell them a number that I&#39;m actually targeting to make at this new position. A lot of jobs will make an offer so close to your last salary that saying a number you&#39;re wanting will put you in a negotiating range where you can say, &quot;Well, I was actually looking to make more than at my last position.&quot;

 R4 [1 hour ago]
 Negotiating tactics apply to salary negotiation as much as they do to other negotiable situations (car buying, flea markets, etc), so if you want to psych yourself up with some general negotiation strategies from across the Internet as well, that can&#39;t hurt. (edited)

 R3 [44 minutes ago]
 Also, keep yourself open to possible company perks, maybe you&#39;d take less $$ if you have more vacation, or work from home days, or really amazing health insurance. It&#39;s not just about salary negotiation. The biggest thing people don&#39;t negotiate for more is vacation, and sometimes can be the easiest to get.


 R4 [39 minutes ago]
 Agreed that the salary number isn&#39;t everything - we hear a lot about &quot;company culture&quot; these days, and a lot of what companies tout as their &quot;culture&quot; is meaningless, so diving into that can also net you a bomb place to work that helps your mental health and personal fulfilment even if it doesn&#39;t pay Google money. Awesome on-site skill-building opportunities? Plenty of experienced people who enjoy mentoring and have helpful attitudes? Tangible, clear, supported diversity initiatives? Strong community/charitable ties? What kinds of &quot;culture&quot; things matter to you?

 R1 [28 minutes ago]
 Agreed. I would work at a place that covers my insurances, and offers more PTO, conference stipends, etc, if the salary is lower because I find those kinds of things very valuable.

 R1 [28 minutes ago]
 Definitely make sure culturally it is a fit for you too. Ask to meet the team before you make any final decisions

 R5
 [15 minutes ago]
 @R1 I really have nothing to add. Dang, write a book!!


 R1 [14 minutes ago]
 hahaha. I’ve heard that before

 R1 [14 minutes ago]
 Maybe i should :thinking_face:


 R2 [14 minutes ago]
 Yes, please!

 R5
 [13 minutes ago]
 Oh, i guess i do have an additional piece of advice: do *not* refer to yourself as a “Junior Developer” (or “junior” anything). Certainly, you don’t the time/experience/etc BUT you do have skills they can use today, and you should have the ability to learn things, but most of all, solve problems


 R5
 [12 minutes ago]
 no one actually knows what the difference between a jr dev and sr dev actually is; it it most certainly not number of years, although that’s often the only thing people think of.

 R2 [12 minutes ago]
 @__ might have something to add, too. I know HackReactor has a lot of opinions on this.

 R5
 [11 minutes ago]
 I might be getting a bit subversive here, but the skills ppl look for in sr people is the ability to be self-directed, take initiative, and most of be able to solve problems

 R2 [10 minutes ago]
 Ha. What makes you “senior” is a whole other giant discussion that I woudl love to have.

 R5
 [10 minutes ago]
 you can most definitely have those; it’s not number of years. sure, someone like me, i’ve just made a huge huge pile of mistakes to learn from, but there’s a lot of sr people who do not bother to learn

 R5
 [10 minutes ago]
 it’s a false label  /  dichotomy

 R5
 [9 minutes ago]
 but it’s one that is so entrenched it’s hard to deal with. so again, do not put that label on yourself

 R5
 [9 minutes ago]
 we need to have another meetup this week so we can have all these great conversations LOL


 R2 [9 minutes ago]
 yep yep yep - hard when that’s often tied to salary, recognition, opportunities, responsibility, etc.

 R1 [9 minutes ago]
 do it!

 R2 [8 minutes ago]
 RIGHT?!

 R1 [8 minutes ago]
 that’s a conversation i would love to be a part of

    #+END_QUOTE



*** Discussion on GDIMPLS Slack
    CAPTURE_DATE: [2017-03-06 Mon 16:17]
    TOPIC:    Y U No Hire Jr Devs?

    OP started off a discussion in the #general chat in
    GDIMpls.slack.com team.

    #+BEGIN_QUOTE
    OP [Today at 1:51 PM]
    question for everybody: have you ever worked at a place that “doesn’t hire jr devs”, spoken to a place/person that “doesn’t hire jr devs”, or do you personally not like jr devs (i won’t be hurt/offended)?

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    so, personally, you gotta know i love jr. devs, otherwise i wouldn&#39;t be trying to help make some :slightly_smiling_face:

    OP [1 hour ago]
    true true

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    but the &quot;we don&#39;t hire jr. devs&quot; is so fucking real

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    i have long convos with recruiters and companies about this alla time. The problem, and I think know it, is that when everyone is hiring sr. devs, that means no one is creating new sr. devs, and you have to hire jr. devs to make sr. devs

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    sorry, I think *everyone* knows it

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    (thinking too fast to type)

    R2 [1 hour ago]
    Yep not many people are willing to put the time in to make the senior devs they truly want by training jr devs.

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    and yet the complaint is that they can&#39;t afford to train jr. devs

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    the typical mindset for tech companies is that they don&#39;t have the time, can&#39;t take the risk, and so on, because they don&#39;t fundamentally understand what they&#39;re trying to make

    R2 [1 hour ago]
    Yep

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    there&#39;s a tremendous lack of mindfulness about developing software, in pretty much any form

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    a lot of this is historical, of course, but that really doesn&#39;t excuse the lack of introspection about what the software industry is

    OP [1 hour ago]
    this is great! I hadn’t thought about that.

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    this also ties into the latest very visible reports of misogyny, we&#39;ve seen, but cuts across all the -isms; where you do not see diversity happening, just talked about and much handwringing

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    you notice women, poc, pwd, etc., when they get someplace primarily because it is so fucking rare

    OP [1 hour ago]
    Diversity &amp; Inclusion -Buzzwords of 2016/17

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    sadly, just buzzwords

    OP [1 hour ago]
    EXACTLY

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    fill out your bingo card!


    R1 [1 hour ago]
    this is not new; i don&#39;t see it changing, i see it getting more lip service, and no real change

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    i don&#39;t think it&#39;s any better

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    and this pisses me off to no end

    R2 [1 hour ago]
    This really has my mind running now. Why arent more companies open to jr devs? Seriously, they have the skills to learn, they have the want, and they require less compensation, why not let them work on your smaller projects until they are your senior dev you want. (edited)

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    and even more, how i have been unable to make and change, and how i&#39;ve been totally complicite

    R1 [1 hour ago]
    i had a phone intreview this morning, and we talked about exactly that, R2

    R2 [45 minutes ago]
    Train the senior devs you want. Why is that so hard?!

    R1 [45 minutes ago]
    how this company *had* hired a bunch of jr. devs, but they had no direction, and no idea of what they should be doing

    R2 [44 minutes ago]
    Yeah thats the opposite problem

    R2 [44 minutes ago]
    they need a leader that wants to and is a good mentor too


    R1 [44 minutes ago]
    and so now they&#39;re looking at getting more sr. people to help with that

    R2 [44 minutes ago]
    Thats good

    R1 [44 minutes ago]
    it&#39;s just another huge example of mindlessness

    R2 [44 minutes ago]
    Yep

    R2 [44 minutes ago]
    Lack of proper planning

    R1 [43 minutes ago]
    what i would love to do, most of all, is help jr. devs become sr. devs


    R1 [43 minutes ago]
    the companies that do hire jr. devs, then proceed to never give them any guidance.

    OP [43 minutes ago]
    I’m interested in why you feel you’ve been complicit @R1

    R2 [42 minutes ago]
    Me too Tamara.

    R2 [42 minutes ago]
    I wish there was a sustainable way to do that. My only idea was winning the lottery so money wasnt a concern, hahaha.

    R1 [41 minutes ago]
    because i fall prey to the same thinking that everyone else does; we had this long convo this weekend at lunch about diversity as it relates to women in tech, and NOT ONCE did anyone, including myself, ever mention the intersectionalities

    R1 [41 minutes ago]
    not. once.

    R3 [41 minutes ago]
    &quot;the companies that do hire jr. devs, then proceed to never give them any guidance.&quot; &lt;-- this is super interesting. (i mean all of this is)

    R1 [40 minutes ago]
    my blue sky pipe dream is that we can open a coop / collective, that isn&#39;t a for profit, and people who participate also have to give back in time and resources

    R3 [40 minutes ago]
    I think that might be part of the hesitation for many. They may want to do it _right_ and convince themselves they don&#39;t have the bandwidth to take on an individual that will need guidance/mentoring/support.

    R1 [40 minutes ago]
    Do understand I am way overgeneralising that

    R2 [40 minutes ago]
    Agreed. I think that is a lot of it. It seems to overwhelming so they just avoid it.

    R3 [40 minutes ago]
    We did this at W______, _very_ intentionally this past year.

    R3 [40 minutes ago]
    Our goal was to hire a &quot;junior&quot; dev

    R1 [40 minutes ago]
    some place have done that, some places do do that

    R2 [39 minutes ago]
    Your pipe dream sounds great R1.

    R3 [38 minutes ago]
    Companies want to make money, and as we discussed at lunch this weekend, assembling and creating a safe place for a diverse team will always create a higher quality product.

    R1 [38 minutes ago]
    what i heard talking with LP last week and this, is an interesting model of organization. A team is 5 people, a lead dev, two jr or other devs, a product mgr, and a UI/UX &quot;specialist&quot; (their term, could be a dev, dunno for sure yet)

    R3 [38 minutes ago]
    I wonder if people don&#39;t actualy believe that, or if they just don&#39;t know how to get there

    R1 [38 minutes ago]
    it&#39;s an interesting model

    R1 [38 minutes ago]
    i think the latter, R3

    R1 [37 minutes ago]
    don&#39;t know, don&#39;t know how to find out, and that&#39;s a huge risk to take

    R3 [37 minutes ago]
    Mhm

    R2 [37 minutes ago]
    That is the perfect team mix, R1, in my mind.

    R1 [37 minutes ago]
    mine to; i hope it&#39;s not just words

    R1 [37 minutes ago]
    i&#39;ve pretty much decided i&#39;ll take their offer if they make one

    R1 [37 minutes ago]
    pls don&#39;t tell

    R2 [36 minutes ago]
    Oh thats super great. So would you be one of those senior devs helping mentor the jr&#39;s?

    R1 [36 minutes ago]
    yeah

    R2 [36 minutes ago]
    My boss mentioned getting a junior &quot;me&quot; (my role, not me specifically) and I was so excited. Mentoring is one of my fave things to do.

    R1 [36 minutes ago]
    i mean, we were all speaking the same language, right? so now all my red flags are flying....

    OP [36 minutes ago]
    this is all really good stuff. And I know that the 3 of you (and more) do want to create that space for those like myself. It’s just really disheartening to be told because I’m a jr dev, I can’t add value

    R1 [35 minutes ago]
    AND THAT IS SO WRONG

    R1 [35 minutes ago]
    IT IS A LIE

    OP [35 minutes ago]
    I KNOW!

    R1 [35 minutes ago]
    spoken by people who are not adding value

    R2 [35 minutes ago]
    That is so horrible. You are amazing and I know you will not let it get you down, but make sure that you do not take that to heart or find it discouraging. (edited)

    OP [35 minutes ago]
    I want to learn the way a company codes, their standards, structure, i want to fix all the little things nobody else does, I want to build shit.


    R2 [34 minutes ago]
    You can add TONS of value.

    OP [34 minutes ago]
    Thank you.

    OP [34 minutes ago]
    It just adds more fuel to an already huge fire

    R2 [34 minutes ago]
    :fire:

    R1 [34 minutes ago]
    i&#39;m not really joking when i say &quot;burn it all down&quot;

    R2 [33 minutes ago]
    You are a strong person, it makes me sad for the people that are less like you. (edited)

    R2 [33 minutes ago]
    The ones that wont have that fight in them and will give up and move on.


    R1 [33 minutes ago]
    but this is also back to relying superheroism to make things better


    OP [32 minutes ago]
    right. That’s another reason why I want to do this at Minnebar

    OP [32 minutes ago]
    because I know that there are so many people that just won’t say anything

    R1 [31 minutes ago]
    you mean have this conversation at Minnebar?

    OP [30 minutes ago]
    yeah, i’m writing up a session called “So you don’t hire Jr Devs? Tell me more.&quot;


    R1 [29 minutes ago]
    oh fuck yeah

    OP [29 minutes ago]
    to speak as a jr dev, how jr devs feel in the market, what can other devs do to support and advocate and our importance

    OP [29 minutes ago]
    and then Lanice and I are also writing up one on Diversity &amp; Inclusion

    R1 [28 minutes ago]
    without jr devs there is no future software business


    R2 [28 minutes ago]
    OMG I am sad, I will miss that.

    R2 [28 minutes ago]
    I will be speaking at WordCamp in San Diego.

    R2 [28 minutes ago]
    Please definitely do that - the world needs to hear it.

    OP [27 minutes ago]
    I am sad you’re missing it too!!

    R1 [26 minutes ago]
    tickets are all gone

    R1 [25 minutes ago]
    also, i hate super large people events

    R1 [24 minutes ago]
    so that&#39;s an example of me being complicit

    R1 [23 minutes ago]
    so, like, what i should say instead, is there anything i can help with?

    R3 [23 minutes ago]
    ^^^^^^^^^^^

    R3 [23 minutes ago]
    that

    R3 [23 minutes ago]
    haha

    R3 [22 minutes ago]
    ditto

    R1 [21 minutes ago]
    &quot;The master&#39;s tools will never dismantle the master&#39;s house&quot; so we make our own tools

    R4 [18 minutes ago]
    This thread just got me really emotional. Thanks to everyone who&#39;s been sharing thoughts and perspectives. As a current junior dev who struggled to find a job and heard from companies that they don&#39;t hire jr, it got really challenging.


    R1 [17 minutes ago]
    This topic is hugely emotional for me as well, cari.tan, it goes into a lot of other things for me as well.

    R1 [16 minutes ago]
    primarily, i think our failing as sr. devs, mgrs, and so on, i.e., the people that *could* change things, is we just do not become or stay mindful

    R4 [16 minutes ago]
    One of the things that I kept thinking about was how if you hire junior devs, then they are coming in and learning your systems, your procedures and it might in someways be easier to integrate into the company processes because they are not bringing in past habits, which might be good and bad.


    R1 [15 minutes ago]
    EXACTLY!! and you&#39;ll have more effective devs than if you wait for the perfect sr. dev to show up

    R1 [14 minutes ago]
    AND! those jr. devs need guidance, attention, (care &amp; feeding?)


    R4 [14 minutes ago]
    I&#39;m currently on a team that doesn&#39;t have any real support for me because I&#39;m the only one working in the area that I work in and I have to go outside of my team when I&#39;m stuck, which can be challenging because of the schedules and workloads of their teams. It gets really hard sometimes.

    R1 [13 minutes ago]
    does you management listen to such issues well?

    R1 [12 minutes ago]
    (i was trying to figure out a way to ask in such a way as to not make any assumptions, but i don&#39;t think i can)

    R4 [12 minutes ago]
    Not really. I&#39;m on contract, which adds some complications. It

    R1 [11 minutes ago]
    certainly

    R1 [10 minutes ago]
    this is another place i have a huge advantage as a sr. dev, even, or especially, on contract, i don&#39;t usually have any hesitations in telling management their organization / communication / processes are not working well

    R4 [10 minutes ago]
    It&#39;s largely due to a restructuring that happened right after I started. I was hired onto a team of six people who all worked on the same parts of the website and then about 3 weeks later we were split across three new teams. I was the only one from the original team that ended up on mine. They are aware, but there&#39;s no real motivation for them to do much about it (add or shift resources, etc).

    R1 [9 minutes ago]
    but it&#39;s not something that a jr. can do with credibility :disappointed:

    R4 [8 minutes ago]
    Yeah, exactly.

    R1 [8 minutes ago]
    start looking for your next contract, maybe


    OP [8 minutes ago]
    i agree.

    R1 [7 minutes ago]
    because, holy cow, fixing their shit is not on you

    R1 [6 minutes ago]
    of course, the other side is get the learning you can out of the current situation

    R1 [5 minutes ago]
    idk, folks, this whole system is not going to solved by waiting for companies to wake up

    R4 [4 minutes ago]
    I have started looking for the next thing. I&#39;ve learned quite a bit, but am definitely ready for something different with more support.

    R1 [4 minutes ago]
    and as much fun as it would be for me to train jr. devs into sr. devs, i also don&#39;t want to just create a chain of cannon fodder

    R1 [3 minutes ago]
    cari.tan : awesome!!

    R4 [3 minutes ago]
    Thanks @OP for starting this conversation. It needs to be talked about and revisited often.

    R1 [3 minutes ago]
    :+1:

    R1 [2 minutes ago]
    i sure want to hear from you all on this

    R1 [2 minutes ago]
    and i am quite serious about the offers of help


    OP [1 minute ago]
    Thank you ALL for contributing. I am glad to know that sr/mid/lead devs care about this

    R4 [1 minute ago]
    Thanks @R1, @R3 and @R2 for being in leadership and senior roles and sharing your perspective and helping to work on this issue!
    #+END_QUOTE

</content>
      <author>
        <name>Tamara Temple</name>
        <email>tamara@tamouse.org</email>
      </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <id>https://github.com/tamouse/swaac/blob/master/posts/Tech/python-notes.org</id>
      <updated>2020-05-23T16:31:19-05:00</updated>
      <title>Python</title>
      <content>* Python
** Python Notes (refile Target)

*** Joining a list of strings with a separator
    :PROPERTIES:
    :CAPTURE_DATE: [2016-12-19 Mon]
    :END:

    This is rather the exact opposite of the way Ruby does it.

    #+BEGIN_SRC python
      sepstr.join(list_of_strings)

      # Example:

      &#39;, &#39;.join([&#39;Apple&#39;,&#39;Pear&#39;,&#39;Banana&#39;,&#39;Orange&#39;])
      # =&gt; &quot;Apple, Pear, Banana, Orange&quot;
    #+END_SRC

    I have not yet understood why this is done this way, but perhaps
    it&#39;s entirely arbitrary.

*** Using boto3 to grab a file from S3
    :PROPERTIES:
    :CAPTURE_DATE: [2016-12-19 Mon 17:18]
    :END:

    Upload a local file to S3:

    #+BEGIN_SRC python
      import boto3

      boto_session = boto3.Session(profile_name=&#39;myaws&#39;)

      boto_session.resource(&#39;s3&#39;).Bucket(&#39;my_bucket&#39;).upload_file(&#39;/tmp/file.txt&#39;, &#39;some/file.txt&#39;)
    #+END_SRC

    This will download a file to the local machine:

    #+BEGIN_SRC python
      import boto3

      boto_session = boto3.Session(profile_name=&#39;myaws&#39;)
      content = boto_session.resource(&#39;s3&#39;).Bucket(&#39;my_bucket&#39;).download_file(&#39;some/file.txt&#39;, &#39;/tmp/somfile.txt&#39;)

    #+END_SRC

    This will pull the file (object) into process memory (careful!)

    #+BEGIN_SRC python
      import boto3

      boto_session = boto3.Session(profile_name=&#39;myaws&#39;)
      content = boto_session.resource(&#39;s3&#39;).Object(&#39;my_bucket&#39;, &#39;some/file.txt&#39;)[&#39;Body&#39;].read()
    #+END_SRC


**** More links on this:

     [[https://gist.github.com/iMilnb/0ff71b44026cfd7894f8][Programmatically manipulate AWS resources with boto3 - a quick
     hands on]]

*** Building a MANIFEST.in template for sdist

    [[https://docs.python.org/2/distutils/sourcedist.html#manifest-template][python docs for MANIFEST.in template]]



*** Magic to make a python script run
    :PROPERTIES:
    :CAPTURE_DATE: [2016-12-20 Tue 11:47]
    :END:


    When writing a python script that defines a bunch of methods,
    classes, and so on, it can be imported into another script to do
    stuff with, or run as an independent script.

    The magic that makes that work is:

    #+BEGIN_SRC python
      if __name__ == &#39;__main__&#39;:
          app.run()
    #+END_SRC

    at the bottom of the file. (~app~ would be defined by the file
    somewhere.)

    Including a shebang at the top will make it interpretable from the
    shell, too.
*** Python ~with~ statement
    :PROPERTIES:
    :CAPTURE_DATE: [2016-12-20 Tue 15:34]
    :LINK:     https://docs.python.org/3/whatsnew/2.6.html#pep-343-the-with-statement
    :TITLE:    What’s New in Python 2.6 — Python 3.5.2 documentation
    :END:

    :CAPTURE_DATE: [2016-12-20 Tue 15:34]
    :LINK:     https://docs.python.org/3/whatsnew/2.6.html#pep-343-the-with-statement
    :TITLE:    What’s New in Python 2.6 — Python 3.5.2 documentation

    The ‘with‘ statement clarifies code that previously would use
    try...finally blocks to ensure that clean-up code is executed. In
    this section, I’ll discuss the statement as it will commonly be
    used. In the next section, I’ll examine the implementation
    details and show how to write objects for use with this
    statement.

    The ‘with‘ statement is a control-flow structure
    whose basic structure is:

    #+BEGIN_SRC python
      with expression [as variable]:
          with-block

    #+END_SRC
*** Ned Batchelder: Lists vs. Tuples
    :PROPERTIES:
    :CAPTURE_DATE: [2017-04-15 Sat 12:13]
    :LINK:     https://nedbatchelder.com/blog/201608/lists_vs_tuples.html
    :TITLE:    Ned Batchelder: Lists vs. Tuples
    :END:

    :CAPTURE_DATE: [2017-04-15 Sat 12:13]
    :LINK:     https://nedbatchelder.com/blog/201608/lists_vs_tuples.html
    :TITLE:    Ned Batchelder: Lists vs. Tuples

    Response to my question in PyLadies#help_me channel.

    To put the Cultural Difference in terms of the C language, lists
    are like arrays, tuples are like structs.
*** Ned Batchelder: Tag: Python
    :PROPERTIES:
    :CAPTURE_DATE: [2017-04-15 Sat 12:16]
    :LINK:     https://nedbatchelder.com/blog/tag/python.html
    :TITLE:    Ned Batchelder: Tag: Python
    :END:

    :CAPTURE_DATE: [2017-04-15 Sat 12:16]
    :LINK:     https://nedbatchelder.com/blog/tag/python.html
    :TITLE:    Ned Batchelder: Tag: Python

    Python Posts by Ned Batchelder; useful info, blogging since 2002.

*** Doctest
    OMG DOCTEST IS DA BOMB!!!

    https://docs.python.org/3/library/doctest.html

    Enter tests in doc strings (Elixir has this too):

    #+BEGIN_SRC python

      SQFT_TO_SQM = 0.09290304

      class CalcArgumentError(Exception):
          def __init__(self, arg, msg):
              self.argument = arg
              self.message = msg


      def calc(length, width):
          &quot;&quot;&quot;

          Calculate the area of a room given length and width

          :returns: (area in sq ft, area in sq meters)

          &gt;&gt;&gt; calc(10.0,5.0)
          (50.0, 4.645152)

          &gt;&gt;&gt; calc(2,2)
          (4.0, 0.37161216)

          &gt;&gt;&gt; calc(&quot;a&quot;, 2)
          Traceback (most recent call last):
              ...
          CalcArgumentError: (&#39;a&#39;, &#39;invalid input: Length must be a number greater than zero&#39;)

          &gt;&gt;&gt; calc(2, &quot;a&quot;)
          Traceback (most recent call last):
              ...
          CalcArgumentError: (&#39;a&#39;, &#39;invalid input: Width must be a number greater than zero&#39;)

          &gt;&gt;&gt; calc(0, 1)
          Traceback (most recent call last):
              ...
          CalcArgumentError: (0.0, &#39;invalid input: Length must be a number greater than zero&#39;)

          &gt;&gt;&gt; calc(1, 0)
          Traceback (most recent call last):
              ...
          CalcArgumentError: (0.0, &#39;invalid input: Width must be a number greater than zero&#39;)



          &quot;&quot;&quot;

          try:
              length = float(length)
              if not length &gt; 0.0:
                  raise ValueError
          except ValueError as err:
              raise CalcArgumentError(length, &quot;invalid input: Length must be a number greater than zero&quot;)

          try:
              width = float(width)
              if not width &gt; 0.0:
                  raise ValueError
          except ValueError as err:
              raise CalcArgumentError(width, &quot;invalid input: Width must be a number greater than zero&quot;)

          area_sqft = length * width
          area_sqm = area_sqft * SQFT_TO_SQM
          return area_sqft, area_sqm

      if __name__ == &#39;__main__&#39;:
          import doctest
          print(&quot;Running Doctests&quot;)
          if (doctest.testmod()[0]) == 0:
              print(&quot;PASSED!&quot;)

    #+END_SRC

    This is so cool. Ruby has one, but it looks *way* out of date, and
    not really much supported. This is first class testing in Python!

*** learn how to deep merge dictionaries in Python               :polyconfig:
    :PROPERTIES:
    :CAPTURE_DATE: [2017-01-27 Fri 08:08]
    :END:
** PySFTP notes
*** Opening a connection using a private key file
    :PROPERTIES:
    :CAPTURE_DATE: [2016-12-19 Mon]
    :END:

    This is pretty straightforward, you can use the ~private_key~
    parameter to give the PEM file:

    #+BEGIN_SRC python
      import pysftp

      with pysftp.Connection(&#39;ftphost&#39;, username=&#39;ftpuser&#39;, private_key=&#39;path/to/pem/file&#39;) as sftp:
          do this
          do that
    #+END_SRC

    *BUT* there&#39;s a huge caveat that I haven&#39;t figured out yet: If the
    host is not yet in the known hosts file, the above fails. The only
    way I could get this to work is to open a connection to the host
    from the command line:

    #+BEGIN_SRC shell-script
      sftp -i path/to/pem/file ftpuser@ftphost
    #+END_SRC

    This opens an interactive connection, which is good enough since it
    stuffs the ftphost into the ~\~/.ssh/known_hosts~ file.

** Flask

*** microblog flask sample application

**** Firebase Config

     Obtained from
     https://console.firebase.google.com/project/microblog-flask-app/overview
     by clicking on &quot;Add Firebase to your web app&quot;.

     ~pyfirebase~ uses only the database URL.


     #+BEGIN_SRC html
       &lt;script src=&quot;https://www.gstatic.com/firebasejs/3.7.3/firebase.js&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
       &lt;script&gt;
         // Initialize Firebase
         var config = {
           apiKey: &quot;&quot;,
           authDomain: &quot;microblog-flask-app.firebaseapp.com&quot;,
           databaseURL: &quot;https://microblog-flask-app.firebaseio.com&quot;,
           storageBucket: &quot;microblog-flask-app.appspot.com&quot;,
           messagingSenderId: &quot;500140812042&quot;,
           serviceAccount: &quot;microblog-flask-app-firebase-adminsdk-ji6au-b353df6573.json&quot;,
         };
         firebase.initializeApp(config);
       &lt;/script&gt;
     #+END_SRC

     #+BEGIN_SRC python
       FIREBASE_CONFIG = {
           &quot;apiKey&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
           &quot;authDomain&quot;: &quot;microblog-flask-app.firebaseapp.com&quot;,
           &quot;databaseURL&quot;: &quot;https://microblog-flask-app.firebaseio.com&quot;,
           &quot;storageBucket&quot;: &quot;microblog-flask-app.appspot.com&quot;,
           &quot;messagingSenderId&quot;: &quot;500140812042&quot;,
           &quot;serviceAccount&quot;: &quot;microblog-flask-app-firebase-adminsdk-ji6au-b353df6573.json&quot;,
       }

     #+END_SRC

**** Firebase Service Account info

     #+BEGIN_SRC javascript
       {
         &quot;type&quot;: &quot;service_account&quot;,
         &quot;project_id&quot;: &quot;microblog-flask-app&quot;,
         &quot;private_key_id&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
         &quot;private_key&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
         &quot;client_email&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
         &quot;client_id&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
         &quot;auth_uri&quot;: &quot;https://accounts.google.com/o/oauth2/auth&quot;,
         &quot;token_uri&quot;: &quot;https://accounts.google.com/o/oauth2/token&quot;,
         &quot;auth_provider_x509_cert_url&quot;: &quot;https://www.googleapis.com/oauth2/v1/certs&quot;,
         &quot;client_x509_cert_url&quot;: &quot;&quot;
       }
     #+END_SRC

**** thisbejim/Pyrebase: A simple python wrapper for the Firebase API.
     :PROPERTIES:
     :CAPTURE_DATE: [2017-03-21 Tue 20:43]
     :LINK:     https://github.com/thisbejim/Pyrebase
     :TITLE:    thisbejim/Pyrebase: A simple python wrapper for the Firebase API.
     :DESCRIPTION: Pyrebase - A simple python wrapper for the Firebase API.
     :END:

     :CAPTURE_DATE: [2017-03-21 Tue 20:43]
     :LINK:     https://github.com/thisbejim/Pyrebase
     :TITLE:    thisbejim/Pyrebase: A simple python wrapper for the Firebase API.
     :DESCRIPTION: Pyrebase - A simple python wrapper for the Firebase API.

     this is current one people suggest using. The ones with the
     highest relevance in PyPi are deprecated!!

** PyLadies
*** Joining Slack

    The PyLadies Slack team has women from all over the world that are
    willing and able to help folks learn.

    Go to http://slackin.pyladies.com/  to sign in (will get approval
    there.)

    On the slack, PyLadiesTC has a channel: ~#twin-cities~

**** Join PyLadies on Slack!
     :PROPERTIES:
     :CAPTURE_DATE: [2017-04-12 Wed 21:35]
     :LINK:     http://slackin.pyladies.com/
     :TITLE:    Join PyLadies on Slack!
     :END:

     :CAPTURE_DATE: [2017-04-12 Wed 21:35]
     :LINK:     http://slackin.pyladies.com/
     :TITLE:    Join PyLadies on Slack!

     How to sign up for the PyLadies Slack team.
** Books
*** NOT recommended
**** Python for the Raspberry Pi
     :PROPERTIES:
     :AUTHORS:  Blum, Bresnahan
     :Copyright: 2016
     :Publisher: Pearson (SAMS imprint)
     :END:

     :AUTHORS:  Blum, Bresnahan
     :Copyright: 2016
     :Publisher: Pearson (SAMS imprint)

     Out of date, covers old versions of the RPi.
</content>
      <author>
        <name>Tamara Temple</name>
        <email>tamara@tamouse.org</email>
      </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <id>https://github.com/tamouse/swaac/blob/master/posts/Tech/provisioning-new-mac.org</id>
      <updated>2020-05-23T16:31:19-05:00</updated>
      <title>Provisioning a new Mac</title>
      <content>* Provisioning a new Mac

*KEY POINT:* the &quot;you&quot; in this writeup is me, the author. If you, the reader, are not me, the author, then you /have to modify to fit your own needs/.

** Admin Privs

If this is your own mac, your account should be created with Administrator privs, and you should be able to install software, do things like run ~sudo~, and all sorts of wonderful things, usually all you need to do is provide your account password when asked.

** Installing Keybase

This stores other credentials for the project, my org files, etc.

1. Go to [[https://keybase.io]] and log in
2. Download the app for the mac from that page
3. Open up the ~dmg~ and follow the prompts to install it
4. Launch the app /Applications/Keybase.app
5. Log in to your keybase account
6. Follow the prompts on the new machine and an old machine you selected to verify the new machine&#39;s identity
7. Log out and log in as the WA admin in the case of the work machine :P
8. Go to the file tab in keybase.app, and install the Finder extension
9. Log out of the WA account and back into the user (use the username instead of real name, i guess...)
10. Go the the file tab in Keybase.app again, open the Finder and see that you have access
11. Go to a new Terminal window, and run ~keybase help~ to make sure the command line works, too

** Other Privs

*** typical areas to find other credentials

- .aws/
- .gnupg/
- .netrc
- .ssh/

*** Keybase-based: getting your creds

The beauty of Keybase is that you can keep credentials and other secrets in the file system for your private use.

The pain is keeping them sync&#39;d.

I have the above directories sync&#39;d to my private keybase folder.

**** saving updating creds to keybase

*NOTE: make sure the directroeis you are copying do NOT have the / at the end!*

#+BEGIN_SRC shell-script
  rsync -av ~/.aws \
	~/.gnupg \
	~/.ssh \
	~/.netrc \
	/Volumes/Keybase/private/tamouse_/creds/
#+END_SRC

**** getting the cred to the new machine

(or just updating them)

#+BEGIN_SRC shell-script
  rsync -av /Volumes/Keybase/private/tamouse_/creds/ $HOME
#+END_SRC

** Install X-Code

This takes a brutally long time, since it&#39;s just such a ginormous download (8G?)

** Install homebrew (brew.sh)

Go out to the [[https://brew.sh][homebrew web page]], there&#39;s a command you can paste into a Terminal window.

At some point, it should ask for your password; give it and then brew will be able to raise its privs when needed.

The last time I did this, I ended up not being able to type at the Terminal. Swiftly just solved by quitting Terminal and restarting it.

Run ~brew doctor~ to make sure everything is cromulent.

*** get ~hub~ program

[[https://hub.github.com/][hub.github.com]] just makes life easier dealing with github:

#+BEGIN_SRC shell-script
  brew install hub
  git config --global hub.protocol https
#+END_SRC

** Download config repos

Since the .ssh creds were copied over in a previous step, this step should be pretty easy.

Remember these are /my configs/; if you are not me, use your own, please.

*** Dot Files

1. clone the dot files repo first: ~git clone git@github.com:tamouse/my-dot-files.git .my-dot-files~
2. move into the new dir: ~pushd .my-dot-files~
3. poke around in the ~profile.d~ folder and make sure all the ones you want are marked as executable
4. in the ~.my-dot-files/~ folder, run ~./setup.sh~ which will set up the links to the various profile and rc files.
5. close the Terminal.app and repen it, the setup stuff should be working. Try it out by typing ~ll~ at the Terminal.

*** Emacs config

1. make sure you&#39;re in the HOME directory again: ~cd~
2. clone the emacs config: ~gcl git@github.com:tamouse/my-emacs-d.git .emacs.d~
3. follow the directions in the README

** Essential Software
*** Installing Emacs

For me, there is next to nothing that is more important that using my imprinted editor. It&#39;s easier than ever these days, too, being able to install as a cask from home brew.

I ran the following to check on stuff: ~brew cask info emacs~ -- in particular, I want a fairly high level version, which might not be completely released. I&#39;m running 26.2, the latest from the command shows 26.3, so it should be good to go.

1. run ~brew cask install emacs~
2. start up emacs with just ~emacs~ to make sure the init.el works as hoped.

   1. on this latest install, i needed to modify init.el
   2. it was making a reference to ~/usr/local/share/emacs/~ which did not exist in this particular install from the home brew cask.
3. test out the ~emacsclient~ aliases:
   
        ecn .


Hopefully everything goes smoothly.

*** Installing Ruby(ies?)

1. Grab ~ruby-install~: ~brew install ruby-install~
2. Get the latest ruby versions: ~ruby-install~
3. Install your sweet version: ~ruby-install ruby 2.5.7~ for the project I&#39;m working for this work computer, others are good, too!
4. Grab ~chruby~: ~brew install chruby~5. Close and reopen the Terminal
6. Run ~chruby~ to verify the ruby you just installed is there
7. For my work machine, I want to always be using the same version of ruby everywhere, so I create a ~.ruby-version~ file with ~ruby-2.5.7~ in it
8. Close and reopen the Terminal again
9. Verify the ruby:
   - ~chruby~ - should show the ruby version you added to the ~.ruby-version~ file
   - ~which ruby~ - should show the new ruby version under your ~.rubies/~ directory
   - ~ruby -v~ - shows the right version of ruby, yay!
10. Install some necessary global gems:
    - bundler - match the version your project(s) need, 2.0.3
    - rake - the version installed with ruby might be okay
    - rails 5.1.6 (or whatever your project uses) (takes a long time, whee)

*** Installing Node, NPM, and friends

We&#39;ll be installing from the nodejs web site, instead of using brew or nvm. 

1. Point the browser at [[https:///nodejs.org/en/]]
2. Click on the LTS version to download the installer
3. Launch the installer, click through confirming everythingss, and it should be good to go.
4. Close and reopen the Terminal, just for good time sake
5. Verify ~node~
   - ~node -v~
   - ~npm -v~
   - ~npx -v~

or do install with brew.  

Install ~yarn~: ~brew install yarn~ (beware there is a new way to do this for yarn v2!)

** Other Software

1. Chrome
2. Firefox
3. LastPass
4. Amphetimine
5. Spark
6. Notion
7. Slack
8. Trello
9. Zoom
10. Affinity Photo &amp; Design
11. Spotify
12. Sonos
13. Monosnap
14. --Spectacle-- use Rectangle instead: https://github.com/rxhanson/Rectangle
15. Alfred
16. Discord
17. Display Menu
18. JetBrains Toolbox (from which you can install the others)
19. Kindle for Mac
20. ... this list will grow :D

** org files

I keep my org files on keybase in git

#+BEGIN_SRC shell
  git clone keybase://private/tamouse_/org-files ~/org
#+END_SRC

** Postgresql

#+BEGIN_SRC shell
  brew install postgresql
  brew services start postgresql
  createdb tamara
#+END_SRC

For other versions run ~brew search postgresql~. you should be able to run different versions of it, but you&#39;ll also need different paths for the data and so on.

** redis

For a lot of work projects, I use redis on the app. It&#39;s generally useful, like PG, so I make sure it&#39;s always available.

#+BEGIN_SRC shell
  brew info redis
  brew install redis
  brew services start redis
#+END_SRC


</content>
      <author>
        <name>Tamara Temple</name>
        <email>tamara@tamouse.org</email>
      </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <id>https://github.com/tamouse/swaac/blob/master/posts/Tech/code-review-notes.org</id>
      <updated>2020-05-23T16:31:19-05:00</updated>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <content>#+TITLE: Notes on conduction guided code reviews

* Introduction

During the course of react web client development, it&#39;s become clear that using our standard method of a team mate reading through a github PR would not work, since the amount of code and files is enormous, contradicting any best practice about doing code reviews. Instead, we&#39;re going to conduct guided code reviews, a practice where we meet as a team to walk through the significant aspects of the code change, to help the other team members understand what is happening and be able to make better contributions to the review.

** Research

*** [[https://www.ibm.com/developerworks/rational/library/11-proven-practices-for-peer-review/index.html][11 Proven Practices for more effective, efficient peer code reviews (IBM Developer)]]

Summary:

1. Review fewer than 200–400 lines of code at a time
2. Aim for an inspection rate of fewer than 300–500 LOC per hour
3. Take enough time for a proper, slow review, but not more than 60–90 minutes
4. Be sure that authors annotate source code before the review begins
5. Establish quantifiable goals for code review, and capture metrics so you can improve your processes
6. Use checklists, because they substantially improve results for both authors and reviewers
7. Verify that the defects are actually fixed
8. Foster a good code review culture in which finding defects is viewed positively
9. Beware of the Big Brother effect
10. Review at least part of the code, even if you can&#39;t do all of it, to benefit from The Ego Effect
11. Adopt lightweight, tool-assisted code reviews


*** [[https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_walkthrough][Software Walkthroughs (Wikipedia)]]

- [[https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/4601584][1028-2008 - IEEE Standard for Software Reviews and Audits]]
- [[http://pesona.mmu.edu.my/~wruslan/SE2/Readings/detail/Reading-6.pdf][IEEE Std 1028-1999 Standard for Software Reviews]] (PDF)


</content>
      <author>
        <name>Tamara Temple</name>
        <email>tamara@tamouse.org</email>
      </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <id>https://github.com/tamouse/swaac/blob/master/posts/Tech/vagrant-notes.org</id>
      <updated>2020-05-14T06:44:09-05:00</updated>
      <title>Vagrant Notes</title>
      <content>* Vagrant Notes
** Making Vagrant boxes go faster

  The typical defaults in the Vagrantfile create a wimpy box.

  My mac has a boatload of RAM and CPU cores to spare, thus making this a better config for working:


#+begin_src diff
   config.vm.provider :virtualbox do |vb|
-    vb.customize [&quot;modifyvm&quot;, :id, &quot;--memory&quot;, 1024]
+    vb.customize [&quot;modifyvm&quot;, :id, &quot;--memory&quot;, 4096, &quot;--vram&quot;, 12, &quot;--cpus&quot;, 4, &quot;--natdnshostresolver1&quot;, &quot;on&quot;]
   end
#+end_src

** Using a resolver to set the box&#39;s IP address
    Instead of hard wiring in an IP address for the vagrant box, you
    can have it look up a name in your host machine&#39;s /etc/hosts file,
    thusly:

    At the top of the Vagrant file:
    #+begin_src ruby
      require &#39;resolve&#39;
    #+end_src

    Then, inside the box configuration:
    #+begin_src ruby
      config.vm.provider :virtualbox do |vb|
        vb.customize [&quot;modifyvm&quot;, &quot;--natdnsresolver1&quot;, &quot;on&quot;]
        #...
      end

      config.vm.network :private_network, ip: Resolv.getaddress(&#39;&lt;vagrant box name from hosts&gt;&#39;)
    #+end_src

    And in your /etc/hosts file:

    #+begin_src
      192.168.80.80	&lt;vagrant box name&gt;
    #+end_src

    Set the IP address to an appropriate setting for your local
    network, and give the vagrant box a suitable name for your project
    and the local network. Using &quot;.dev&quot; as the tld should be good.
</content>
      <author>
        <name>Tamara Temple</name>
        <email>tamara@tamouse.org</email>
      </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <id>https://github.com/tamouse/swaac/blob/master/posts/Tech/ux-notes.org</id>
      <updated>2020-05-14T06:44:09-05:00</updated>
      <title>UX Notes</title>
      <content>* UX Notes
** [[http://www.givegoodux.com/4-tips-adding-lean-ux-agile-development-process/][4 Tips for Adding Lean UX to an Agile Development Process]]

    As organizations of all shapes and sizes come to grips with the fact that UX is critical to project and product success, a common question resurfaces time and again:

    “How do we add Lean UX practices to our current process?”

    1) Hire experienced UX analysts and designers; you need at least one
       experienced, senior UX member capable of sharing the driving.

    2) There must be an “Iteration 0” in your process where “just
       enough” research, modeling and design happens.

    3) Follow a process where UX, design and development work is “chunked”
       and starts with the core, most broad-reaching areas of features and
       functionality.

    4) Use a collaborative, parallel work process to keep UX efforts
       both ahead and behind development efforts.

    capture date: [2015-03-19 Thu 16:30]
** [[http://semantic-ui.com/][Semantic UI Toolkit]]
   Date: &lt;2013-10-15 Tue 02:19&gt;

   UI is the vocabulary of the web.

   Semantic empowers designers and developers by creating a language
   for sharing UI.

   Semantic is an alternative to Twitter Bootstrap and other UI
   kits. It seems like it&#39;s a more readable and usable thing to me. It
   also is something that seems more easily customizable. It will be
   interesting to see how it plays out.

   Currently looking at using it on a few new sites, along with
   [[middleman]].
</content>
      <author>
        <name>Tamara Temple</name>
        <email>tamara@tamouse.org</email>
      </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
      <id>https://github.com/tamouse/swaac/blob/master/posts/Tech/thor-notes.org</id>
      <updated>2020-05-14T06:44:09-05:00</updated>
      <title>thor-notes</title>
      <content>** Thor Notes

*** Start here for next thor project

    Seriously, this has so much &quot;stock&quot; stuff:

    https://github.com/tamouse/rearrange_books/tree/start-here-for-next-thor-project

**** turn this thing into a thor thor generator!
     Dude, as if you&#39;re the first person to do this?


*** Giving a task multiple arguments

    Q: How can I have a task get multiple arguments, like many regular
    POSIX commands?

    Example:

    #+BEGIN_SRC shell-script
      cp source_file source_file source_file source_file ... dest_dir
    #+END_SRC

    Pretty simple:

    #+BEGIN_SRC ruby
      desc &quot;taskname ARGLIST&quot;
      def taskname(*args)
      end
    #+END_SRC

    would let you do:

    #+BEGIN_SRC shell-script
      thor taskname arg1 arg2 arg3 arg4
    #+END_SRC

    and ~args~ in the task would be ~[&quot;arg1&quot;, &quot;arg2&quot;, &quot;arg3&quot;, &quot;arg4&quot;]~



*** Invoke a thor task by giving only a class option
    :PROPERTIES:
    :CAPTURE_DATE: [2016-11-06 Sun 01:11]
    :END:

    From stackoverflow: http://stackoverflow.com/a/7311357/742446

    [...use] Thor.map to invoke a command by only giving an
    option flag:

    #+BEGIN_SRC ruby
      map &#39;-F&#39; =&gt; &#39;foo&#39;
    #+END_SRC

    Now you can also pass parameters

    #+BEGIN_SRC ruby
      mythorcommand -F bar # =&gt; invokes foo(&quot;bar&quot;)
    #+END_SRC

    answered Sep 5 &#39;11 at 17:57 by tfischbach

*** Give thor a default task
    :PROPERTIES:
    :CAPTURE_DATE: [2016-11-06 Sun 01:13]
    :END:

    From stackoverflow: http://stackoverflow.com/a/23955971/742446

    I found a rather &#39;strange&#39; solution for this problem that is working quite well with me.

    You add a default task to Thor. Than you add the method_missing so
    that you can trick Thor into passing the default method as an
    argument if there are parameters to your application.

    Taking from your example, the solution would look like this:

    #+BEGIN_SRC ruby
      class MyThorCommand &lt; Thor
	default_task :my_default

	desc &quot;my_default&quot;, &quot;A simple default&quot;
	def my_default(*args)
          puts args.inspect
	end

	def method_missing(method, *args)
          args = [&quot;my_default&quot;, method.to_s] + args
          MyThorCommand.start(args)
	end

      end

      MyThorCommand.start(ARGV)
    #+END_SRC

    If this is in the file &quot;my_thor.rb&quot; an execution &quot;ruby my_thor.rb
    foo bar&quot; would show &#39;[&quot;foo&quot;, &quot;bar&quot;]&#39; as a result.

    answered May 30 &#39;14 at 13:38 by Edu

*** Making Thor scripts colourful

   capture date: [2015-10-11 Sun 02:06]

   In Thor::Actions, the various output commands can be made nicely
   colourful. You can append symbols representing various colours after
   the output string. For example:

   #+begin_src ruby
     say &quot;This will make you green with envy&quot;, :green
     say &quot;Don&#39;t be sad&quot;, :blue
     say &quot;ACK! AN ERROR!&quot;, :red
   #+end_src

   Colour symbols are defined in
   https://github.com/erikhuda/thor/blob/master/lib/thor/shell/color.rb


   #+begin_src ruby
     # Set color by using a string or one of the defined constants. If a third
     # option is set to true, it also adds bold to the string. This is based
     # on Highline implementation and it automatically appends CLEAR to the end
     # of the returned String.
     #
     # Pass foreground, background and bold options to this method as
     # symbols.
     #
     # Example:
     #
     #   set_color &quot;Hi!&quot;, :red, :on_white, :bold
     #
     # The available colors are:
     #
     #   :bold
     #   :black
     #   :red
     #   :green
     #   :yellow
     #   :blue
     #   :magenta
     #   :cyan
     #   :white
     #   :on_black
     #   :on_red
     #   :on_green
     #   :on_yellow
     #   :on_blue
     #   :on_magenta
     #   :on_cyan
     #   :on_white

   #+end_src
</content>
      <author>
        <name>Tamara Temple</name>
        <email>tamara@tamouse.org</email>
      </author>
    </entry>
</feed>
